<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Spring-data | Coding Forest]]></title>
  <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/categories/spring-data/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-10-24T23:22:37-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Juan Ignacio Vimberg]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oracle, JPA and the Mystery of the String That Was Null]]></title>
    <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2018/06/23/oracle-jpa-and-the-mistery-of-the-string-that-was-null/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-23T10:34:26-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2018/06/23/oracle-jpa-and-the-mistery-of-the-string-that-was-null</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the story of how Oracle DB was messing up Kotlin’s type system, and what I did to fix it.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The setup</h2>

<p>Let’s start by <em>setting the stage</em>, for this particular project I was working with the following stack:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2018-06-23/Stack.png" width="720" title="’Spring + Data + Kotlin + Oracle’" ></p>

<h2>The problem</h2>

<p>So I had modeled the following <strong>Entity</strong> leveraging Kotlin’s <a href="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/reference/data-classes.html">data classes</a><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>:</p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code" data-highlight-only>
import javax.persistence.Entity
import javax.persistence.Id

//sampleStart
@Entity
data class Person(
    val name: String,
    @Id val id: Long? = null
)
//sampleEnd
</xmp>


<p>Tests where passing with flying colors, but for some reason we were noticing that <strong>the <em>name</em> would sometimes come back as <code>null</code></strong> even thought it was typed as <code>String</code> and not <code>String?</code>.</p>

<h2>The analysis</h2>

<p>To make things more difficult there where other failures in the communication layer masking the real issue. But we finally figured out what was happening when we notice <strong>it was only reproducible under the following conditions</strong>:</p>

<ul>
<li>The property <code>name</code> was empty</li>
<li>Not reproducible on tests</li>
<li>Persisting to <em>OracleDB</em> (instead of embedded H2)</li>
</ul>


<p>That’s when I discovered:
<blockquote><p>This is because Oracle internally changes empty string to NULL values. Oracle simply won&rsquo;t let insert an empty string.</p><footer><strong>Some guy on Stack Overflow <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/13278879/1499171">https://stackoverflow.com/a/13278879/1499171</a></strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>So when the data was mapped back to my <code>Person</code> object I ended up with a <code>null</code> value for <em>name</em>. This is probably only possible because <strong>Hibernate is using reflection to set the field value</strong> in runtime, thus breaking Kotlin’s <a href="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/reference/null-safety.html">null safety</a>.</p>

<h2>What I did about it</h2>

<p>The funny thing about this one is that <strong>there is not much you can do about it</strong>. <em>There is no magic configuration to tell Oracle how you want to handle empty strings.</em> Yes there are some hacks like changing <code>""</code> to <code>" "</code> but I’d rather invent a random <em>name</em> for the guy than persisting a whitespace.</p>

<p>The silver lining is that most of the time <strong>if you’re not allowing null values you probably don’t want an empty string either</strong>. Now YMMV but I know this was true for a person’s name.</p>

<p>In fact you might even want to <strong>implement a more strict validation</strong> so people can’t be named: “💩”.</p>

<h3>Testing</h3>

<p>First thing I did was to try to reproduce this using a test. But since I was using <code>@DataJpaTest</code> with H2 embedded DB empty strings where empty strings an nulls where nulls. So the issue was <strong>not reproducible</strong>.</p>

<p>That’s when I learned that you <strong>can tell H2 to behave like an Oracle DB</strong> using <a href="http://www.h2database.com/html/features.html">Oracle Compatibility mode</a>. To achieve this I added the following configuration to my <code>application.yml</code> under <code>test/resources</code>:</p>

<pre><code>spring:
  datasource:
    url: jdbc:h2:mem:testdb;Mode=Oracle
</code></pre>

<p>And annotated my test class with:</p>

<pre><code class="java">@RunWith(SpringRunner::class)
@DataJpaTest
@AutoConfigureTestDatabase(replace = AutoConfigureTestDatabase.Replace.NONE)
class FormRepositoryTest {…}
</code></pre>

<p>And <em>voilà</em>, now you have an <strong>H2 in memory DB dressed up as Oracle</strong>.</p>

<h3>Changing the schema</h3>

<p>The other thing I realized is that <strong>the schema allowed for <code>null</code> values</strong> on the <em>name</em> column. I’d been using <code>javax.persistence.schema-generation</code> as a starting point for my schema and <strong>I wrongly assumed</strong> it would take the hint from the Kotlin type system to prevent null values<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.</p>

<p>Instead I had to explicitly annotate my Entity:</p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code" data-highlight-only>
import javax.persistence.Entity
import javax.persistence.Id

//sampleStart
@Entity
data class Person(
    @Column(nullable = false) val name: String,
    @Id val id: Long? = null
)
//sampleEnd
</xmp>


<p>and manually change my existing schema</p>

<pre><code>CREATE TABLE Person (
  id NUMBER(19, 0) NOT NULL,
  name VARCHAR2(255 CHAR) NOT NULL,
  PRIMARY KEY (id)
);
</code></pre>

<p>The result is that now if somebody tries to persist a Person with an empty name a <strong>big fat Exception is thrown</strong>. Or at least until I implement proper name validation.</p>

<script src="https://unpkg.com/kotlin-playground@1" data-selector=".kotlin-code"></script>



<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>If I had a dollar for every time I modeled a Person…<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>It would be nice right?<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
