<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Soft Skills | What I learned today]]></title>
  <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/categories/soft-skills/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-15T19:11:53-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Juan Ignacio Vimberg]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Make People Like You (HTWFAIP - Part 2)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2014/11/15/how-to-make-people-like-you-htwfaip-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-15T18:57:40-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2014/11/15/how-to-make-people-like-you-htwfaip-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Second post of the <a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/categories/htwfaip/">series</a> on the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Win-Friends-Influence-People/dp/0671027034">&ldquo;How to Win Friends and Influence People&rdquo;</a> by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dale_Carnegie">Dale Carnegie</a>. I know, <strong>How to make people like you</strong> sounds soooo lame, but stick with me, this is a good chapter.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>1. Become genuinely interested in other people</h3>

<p>You can make more friends in two months by becoming interested in other people than you can in two years by trying to get other people interested in you.</p>

<h3>2. Smile!</h3>

<p>Like a dog, show that you are happy to see people. Smile even when talking on the phone. Happiness doesn’t depend on outward conditions. It depends on inner conditions. ‘A man without a smiling face must not open a shop.’</p>

<h3>3. Remember that a person’s name is to that person the sweetest sound in any language</h3>

<p>Napoleon’s advice on remembering names: If he didn’t get the name distinctly, he said, “So sorry. I didn’t get the name clearly.” Then, if it was an unusual name, he would say, “How is it spelled?” During the conversation, he took the trouble to repeat the name several times, and tried to associate it in his mind with the person’s features, expression and general appearance.</p>

<h3>4. Be a good listener</h3>

<p>Encourage others to talk about themselves: &ldquo;She didn’t want to hear me talk about my travels. All she wanted was an interested listener, so she could expand her ego and tell about where she had been.&rdquo; Exclusive attention to the person who is speaking to you is very important. Nothing else is so flattering as that. Ask questions that the other  person will enjoy answering. A friend often doesn’t want advice, but just a friendly, sympathetic listener. A person’s toothache means more to that person than a famine in China which kills a million people, think of that the next time you start a conversation.</p>

<h3>5. Talk in terms of the other person’s interests</h3>

<p>Whenever Roosevelt expected a visitor, he sat up late the night before, reading up on the subject in which he knew his guest was particularly interested.</p>

<h3>6. Make the other person feel important—and do it sincerely</h3>

<p>Little phrases such as ‘I’m sorry to trouble you,’ ‘Would you be so kind as to – ?’ ‘Won’t you please?’ ‘Would you mind?’ ‘Thank you’ – little courtesies like these oil the cogs of the monotonous grind of everyday life – and incidentally, they are the hallmark of good breeding. The unvarnished truth is that almost all the people you meet feel themselves superior to you in some way, and a sure way to their hearts is to let them realise in some subtle way that you realise their importance, and recognise it sincerely. ‘Talk to people about themselves and they will listen for hours.’</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Handling People (HTWFAIP - Part 1)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2014/11/02/handling-people-htwfaip-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-02T13:50:13-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2014/11/02/handling-people-htwfaip-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the first of a <a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/categories/htwfaip/">series of posts</a> on the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Win-Friends-Influence-People/dp/0671027034">&ldquo;How to Win Friends and Influence People&rdquo;</a> by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dale_Carnegie">Dale Carnegie</a>. Today: <strong>Handling People</strong>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>1. Don&rsquo;t criticize condemn or complain</h3>

<p>Criticism is futile because it puts a person on the defensive and usually makes him strive to justify himself. Criticism is dangerous, because it wounds a person’s precious pride, hurts his sense of importance, and arouses resentment.</p>

<h3>2. Give sincere and honest appreciation</h3>

<p>Everyone wants to feel important. We usually spend about 95 percent of our time thinking about ourselves. Be hearty in your approbation and lavish in your praise. Think of the other person’s good points, so you won’t have to resort to flattery. Try leaving a friendly trail of little sparks of gratitude on your daily trips.</p>

<h3>3. Arouse in the other person an eager want</h3>

<p> Talk about what they want and show them how to get it. Henry Ford: “If there is any one secret of success, it lies in the ability to get the other person’s point of view and see things from that person’s angle as well as from your own.”</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
