<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Soft Skills | Coding Forest]]></title>
  <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/categories/soft-skills/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-01-13T21:59:17-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Juan Ignacio Vimberg]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Be a Leader (HTWFAIP - Part 4)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2015/06/15/be-a-leader-htwfaip-part-4/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-15T07:37:31-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2015/06/15/be-a-leader-htwfaip-part-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last installment of the <a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/categories/htwfaip/">series</a>. 9 Tips to become the leader you&rsquo;d like to follow.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Begin with praise and honest appreciation</h3>

<p>It is always easier to listen to unpleasant things after we have heard some praise of our good points. This is also sometimes refered as the <a href="http://lifehacker.com/297247/give-constructive-criticism">&ldquo;sandwich rule&rdquo;</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2015-06-15/SandwichRule.jpg" width="250" title="&lsquo;Sandwich Rule&rsquo;" ></p>

<h3>How to Criticize: Call attention to people’s mistakes indirectly</h3>

<p>Change the word &lsquo;but&rsquo; to &lsquo;and&rsquo;. For example: a man carefully polished a sermon and showed it to his wife, instead of talking about its many faults, she said she thought it would be a great article for some journal. Be subtle about criticism.</p>

<h3>Talk about your own mistakes before criticizing</h3>

<p>In order to build rapport with the person you are criticising, start by talking about your own mistakes. You can use phrases like: &ldquo;When I was your age, I too struggled with&hellip;&rdquo; or &ldquo;When I was at your level of experience, I too thought that&hellip;&rdquo;.</p>

<h3>Ask questions instead of giving direct orders</h3>

<p>Gave suggestions, not orders. Let people do things for themselves and make their own mistakes. Asking questions not only makes an order more palatable; it often stimulates the creativity of the persons whom you ask. <strong>People are more likely to accept an order if they have had a part in the decision that caused the order to be issued.</strong></p>

<h3>Let the other person save face</h3>

<p>A few minutes’ thought, a considerate word or two, or a genuine understanding of the other person’s attitude can go a long way to alleviating the sting of criticism. Antoine de Saint-Exupery once said: <em>“I have no right to say or do anything that diminishes a man in his own eyes. What matters is not what I think of him, but what he thinks of himself. Hurting a man in his dignity is a crime.”</em></p>

<h3>Praise every improvement, no matter how slight</h3>

<p>Take every chance you&rsquo;ve got to sincerly praise someone. Everybody likes to be praised, but when praise is specific, it comes across as sincere – not something the other person may be saying just to make one feel good. <strong>Nobody wants flattery!</strong></p>

<h3>Give the person a fine reputation to live up to</h3>

<p>In short, if you want to improve a person in a certain respect, act as though that particular trait were already one of his or her outstanding characteristics. Give them a fine reputation to live up to, and they will make prodigious efforts rather than see you disillusioned.</p>

<h3>Make a fault seem easy to correct</h3>

<p>Make the thing seem easy to do, let the other person know that you have faith in his ability to do it, that he has an undeveloped flair for it – and he will practise until the dawn comes in the window in order to excel.</p>

<h3>Make the other person happy about doing what you suggest</h3>

<p>When you make your request, put it in a form that will convey to the other person the idea that he personally will benefit. <em>&lsquo;He had a delightful way of putting things; he created the impression that by accepting this great honour I would be doing him a favour.&rsquo;</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Win People to Your Way of Thinking (HTWFAIP - Part 3)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2014/12/21/win-people-to-your-way-of-thinking-htwfaip-part-3/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-21T18:53:16-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2014/12/21/win-people-to-your-way-of-thinking-htwfaip-part-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Third post of the <a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/categories/htwfaip/">series</a>. Today: some advice on how to convince people to your way of thinking. This is a long, but juicy post.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>1. You can’t win an argument</h3>

<p>If you argue and rankle and contradict, you may achieve a victory sometimes; but it will be an empty victory because you will never get your opponent’s good will (&ldquo;You have made him feel inferior. You have hurt his pride. He will resent your triumph.&rdquo;). Distrust your first instinctive impression. Our first natural reaction in a disagreeable situation is to be defensive. Be careful. Listen first. Give your opponents a chance to talk. Let them finish. Do not resist, defend or debate. This only raises barriers. Try to build bridges of understanding. Don’t build higher barriers of misunderstanding. Look for areas of agreement. When you have heard your opponents out, dwell first on the points and areas on which you agree. Be honest. Look for areas where you can admit error and say so. Apologize for your mistakes. It will help disarm your opponents and reduce defensiveness. Thank your opponents sincerely for their interest. Anyone who takes the time to disagree with you is interested in the same things you are. Think of them as people who really want to help you, and you may turn your opponents into friends.</p>

<h3>2. Show respect for the other person’s opinions</h3>

<p>Never say, “You’re wrong.”: Never begin by announcing ‘I am going to prove so-and-so to you.’ That’s bad. Do it so subtly, so adroitly, that no one will feel that you are doing it. You will never get into trouble by admitting that you may be wrong. That will stop all argument and inspire your opponent to be just as fair and open and broad-minded as you are. It will make him want to admit that he, too, may be wrong.</p>

<h3>3. When wrong, admit it quickly and emphatically</h3>

<p>Say about yourself all the derogatory things you know the other  person is thinking or wants to say—and say them before that person has a chance to. The chances are a hundred to one that a generous, forgiving attitude will be taken and your mistakes will be minimised.</p>

<h3>4. Begin in a friendly way</h3>

<p>Gentleness and friendliness were always stronger than fury and force.</p>

<h3>5. Get the other person saying “yes, yes”</h3>

<p>Begin by emphasising – and keep on emphasising – the things on which you agree. Keep emphasising, if possible, that you are both striving for the same end and that your only difference is one of method and not of purpose. The skillful speaker gets, at the outset, a number of ‘Yes’ responses.</p>

<h3>6. Let the other person do lots of the talking</h3>

<p>Let the other people talk themselves out. They know more about their business and problems than you do. So ask them questions. Let them tell you a few things. Almost every successful person likes to reminisce about his early struggles.</p>

<h3>7. Let the other person feel ownership of the idea</h3>

<p>No one likes to feel that he or she is being sold something or told to do a thing. We much prefer to feel that we are buying of our own accord or acting on our own ideas. We like to be consulted about our wishes, our wants, our thoughts.</p>

<h3>8. Try honestly to see things from the other  person’s point of view</h3>

<p>Success in dealing with people depends on a sympathetic grasp of the other person’s viewpoint. ‘I would rather walk the sidewalk in front of a person’s office for two hours before an interview,’ said Dean Donham of the Harvard business school, ‘than step into that office without a perfectly clear idea of what I was going to say and what that person – from my knowledge of his or her interests and motives – was likely to answer.’</p>

<h3>9. Be sympathetic towards the other person’s ideas and desires</h3>

<p>The magic words: “I don’t blame you one iota for feeling as you do. If I were you I’d undoubtedly feel the same.” And mean it!</p>

<h3>10. Appeal to the nobler motives</h3>

<p>If you have no other evidence, assume that a customer is honest, truthful, and willing to pay the charges if they are convinced that they are correct.Even those who aren’t naturally honest will often react well if you show that you consider them to be honest and fair.</p>

<h3>11. Dramatize your idea</h3>

<p>Merely stating a truth isn’t enough. The truth has to be made vivid, interesting, dramatic. You have to use showmanship.</p>

<h3>12. Throw down a challenge</h3>

<p>People love the work they are doing, and being great at it.Charles Schwab: “The way to get things done is to stimulate competition. I do not mean in a sordid, money-getting way, but in the desire to excel.”</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Make People Like You (HTWFAIP - Part 2)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2014/11/15/how-to-make-people-like-you-htwfaip-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-15T18:57:40-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2014/11/15/how-to-make-people-like-you-htwfaip-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Second post of the <a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/categories/htwfaip/">series</a> on the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Win-Friends-Influence-People/dp/0671027034">&ldquo;How to Win Friends and Influence People&rdquo;</a> by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dale_Carnegie">Dale Carnegie</a>. I know, <strong>How to make people like you</strong> sounds soooo lame, but stick with me, this is a good chapter.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>1. Become genuinely interested in other people</h3>

<p>You can make more friends in two months by becoming interested in other people than you can in two years by trying to get other people interested in you.</p>

<h3>2. Smile!</h3>

<p>Like a dog, show that you are happy to see people. Smile even when talking on the phone. Happiness doesn’t depend on outward conditions. It depends on inner conditions. ‘A man without a smiling face must not open a shop.’</p>

<h3>3. Remember that a person’s name is to that person the sweetest sound in any language</h3>

<p>Napoleon’s advice on remembering names: If he didn’t get the name distinctly, he said, “So sorry. I didn’t get the name clearly.” Then, if it was an unusual name, he would say, “How is it spelled?” During the conversation, he took the trouble to repeat the name several times, and tried to associate it in his mind with the person’s features, expression and general appearance.</p>

<h3>4. Be a good listener</h3>

<p>Encourage others to talk about themselves: &ldquo;She didn’t want to hear me talk about my travels. All she wanted was an interested listener, so she could expand her ego and tell about where she had been.&rdquo; Exclusive attention to the person who is speaking to you is very important. Nothing else is so flattering as that. Ask questions that the other  person will enjoy answering. A friend often doesn’t want advice, but just a friendly, sympathetic listener. A person’s toothache means more to that person than a famine in China which kills a million people, think of that the next time you start a conversation.</p>

<h3>5. Talk in terms of the other person’s interests</h3>

<p>Whenever Roosevelt expected a visitor, he sat up late the night before, reading up on the subject in which he knew his guest was particularly interested.</p>

<h3>6. Make the other person feel important—and do it sincerely</h3>

<p>Little phrases such as ‘I’m sorry to trouble you,’ ‘Would you be so kind as to – ?’ ‘Won’t you please?’ ‘Would you mind?’ ‘Thank you’ – little courtesies like these oil the cogs of the monotonous grind of everyday life – and incidentally, they are the hallmark of good breeding. The unvarnished truth is that almost all the people you meet feel themselves superior to you in some way, and a sure way to their hearts is to let them realise in some subtle way that you realise their importance, and recognise it sincerely. ‘Talk to people about themselves and they will listen for hours.’</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Handling People (HTWFAIP - Part 1)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2014/11/02/handling-people-htwfaip-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-02T18:50:13-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2014/11/02/handling-people-htwfaip-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the first of a <a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/categories/htwfaip/">series of posts</a> on the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Win-Friends-Influence-People/dp/0671027034">&ldquo;How to Win Friends and Influence People&rdquo;</a> by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dale_Carnegie">Dale Carnegie</a>. Today: <strong>Handling People</strong>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>1. Don&rsquo;t criticize condemn or complain</h3>

<p>Criticism is futile because it puts a person on the defensive and usually makes him strive to justify himself. Criticism is dangerous, because it wounds a person’s precious pride, hurts his sense of importance, and arouses resentment.</p>

<h3>2. Give sincere and honest appreciation</h3>

<p>Everyone wants to feel important. We usually spend about 95 percent of our time thinking about ourselves. Be hearty in your approbation and lavish in your praise. Think of the other person’s good points, so you won’t have to resort to flattery. Try leaving a friendly trail of little sparks of gratitude on your daily trips.</p>

<h3>3. Arouse in the other person an eager want</h3>

<p> Talk about what they want and show them how to get it. Henry Ford: “If there is any one secret of success, it lies in the ability to get the other person’s point of view and see things from that person’s angle as well as from your own.”</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
