<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Kotlin | Coding Forest]]></title>
  <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/categories/kotlin/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-07-20T16:24:46-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Juan Ignacio Vimberg]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing Githooks in Kotlin]]></title>
    <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2018/07/03/writing-githooks-in-kotlin/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-03T19:45:28-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2018/07/03/writing-githooks-in-kotlin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You’re already using Kotlin on your codebase. Maybe, you’ve even migrated to the new <a href="https://github.com/gradle/kotlin-dsl">Kotlin DSL for Gradle</a>. Wouldn’t it be nice if you could use Kotlin for your <a href="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Customizing-Git-Git-Hooks">git hooks</a> too?</p>

<!--more-->


<p><strong>Well, turns out you can!</strong> Here’s how you do it…</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2018-07-04/captain-hook.png" title="’Captain githook’" ></p>

<h2>What do I need?</h2>

<p>Git will basically run whatever script you drop on the <code>.git/hooks</code> directory. In their words:</p>

<blockquote><p>To enable a hook script, put a file in the hooks subdirectory of your <code>.git</code> directory that is named appropriately (without any extension) and is executable</p></blockquote>

<p>So all we need is to be able to execute Kotlin files as scripts. There is a <a href="https://github.com/Kotlin/KEEP/blob/scripting/proposals/scripting-support.md">Kotlin Scripting Support KEEP</a> under definition. But for the time being <strong>we’ll stick with the awesome <a href="https://github.com/holgerbrandl/kscript">KScript library</a> (by <a href="https://github.com/holgerbrandl">@holgerbrandl</a>)</strong> that enables Kotlin scripting on <em>*nix-based</em> systems.</p>

<p>You can find the details for installing KScript <a href="https://github.com/holgerbrandl/kscript#installation">here</a>. On MacOS if you’re using <a href="https://brew.sh/">Homebrew</a> all you have to do is run: <code>brew install holgerbrandl/tap/kscript</code>.</p>

<p>I’ll also be using <strong>Gradle</strong> to automatically install the githook and run the proper validation, but the same can be done with <strong>Maven</strong>.</p>

<h2>The script</h2>

<p>As an example I’m going to show how to do a <strong>pre-push client hook</strong> that aborts the push if <code>grade check</code> task is not successful. For this I’ve created a file named <code>Pre-Push.kts</code>:</p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code" data-highlight-only>
//sampleStart
#!/usr/bin/env kscript

import java.io.File

println("${Constants.SCRIPT_LOG_TAG} Running pre-push hook")
val hasStashed = stash()
if (hasStashed) {
    println("${Constants.SCRIPT_LOG_TAG} Stashing uncommited changes")
}

val checkExistStatus = runCheck()

if (hasStashed) {
    println("${Constants.SCRIPT_LOG_TAG} Unstashing your changes")
    unstash()
}

val exitValue = when {
    checkExistStatus != Constants.SUCCESS_EXIT_VALUE -> {
        println("${Constants.SCRIPT_LOG_TAG} Gradle check failed. I'm sorry but you can't continue with your push")
        Constants.ERROR_EXIT_VALUE
    }
    else -> {
        println("${Constants.SCRIPT_LOG_TAG} Everything went fine. You can continue with your push")
        Constants.SUCCESS_EXIT_VALUE
    }
}

kotlin.system.exitProcess(exitValue)
//sampleEnd

fun runCheck(): ExitStatus {
    println("${Constants.SCRIPT_LOG_TAG} Running gradle check")
    return "gradle check".runCommandWithRedirect()
}

fun stash(): Boolean {
    val stashOutput = """git stash push --include-untracked -m "stash created by pre-push hook"""".runCommand()
    return stashOutput.firstOrNull() != Constants.NOTHING_TO_STASH_MSG
}

fun unstash() = "git stash pop -q".runCommand()

fun String.runCommand(dir: File? = null): Sequence<String> =
    ProcessBuilder("/bin/sh", "-c", this)
        .redirectErrorStream(true)
        .directory(dir)
        .start()
        .inputStream.bufferedReader().lineSequence()

// Redirecting output and error to stdout
fun String.runCommandWithRedirect(dir: File? = null): ExitStatus =
    ProcessBuilder("/bin/sh", "-c", this)
        .redirectErrorStream(true)
        .inheritIO()
        .directory(dir)
        .start()
        .waitFor()

object Constants {
    const val SCRIPT_LOG_TAG = "Pre-push -"
    const val NOTHING_TO_STASH_MSG = "No local changes to save"
    const val SUCCESS_EXIT_VALUE = 0
    const val ERROR_EXIT_VALUE = -1
}

typealias ExitStatus = Int
</xmp>


<p>The first line is all the <em>magic incantation</em> we need to execute the script. By setting the shebang to <code>#!/usr/bin/env kscript</code> we get to use <code>kscript</code> as <a href="https://github.com/holgerbrandl/kscript#interpreter-usage">interpreter for the script</a>.</p>

<p>The code after the import is <strong>the actual script</strong>. Those are the lines that are going to be executed as soon as somebody calls the script. <em>Just as you’d expect with any regular shell script.</em></p>

<p>In a nutshell this is what the script does:</p>

<ol>
<li>Stash uncommitted changes <em>if any</em><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></li>
<li>Run code validation (in this case <code>gradle check</code>)</li>
<li>Unstash possible changes stashed on <em>step 1</em></li>
<li>Log outcome and set the proper exit value</li>
</ol>


<p>The last step is important because <strong>if the script exits to anything other than 0 then git aborts the action</strong> (in this case the push).</p>

<h3>How do I call things from a script?</h3>

<p>To do anything useful on your script you’ll probably have to <strong>call some external tool</strong> at some point. In this particular case for example a mix of <em>git commands</em> and <em>gradle tasks</em>.</p>

<p>There are 2 ways you can go about this:</p>

<ol>
<li>Either <strong>use a Kotlin/Java library</strong> for the task you’re trying to accomplish (in this example we could use <a href="https://www.eclipse.org/jgit/">JGit</a> and <a href="https://docs.gradle.org/current/userguide/embedding.html">Gradle tooling API</a>)</li>
<li>Or <strong>call a shell command</strong> directly</li>
</ol>


<p>While the first approach is more <strong>portable</strong>, it will introduce some dependencies to your script (which fortunately <a href="https://github.com/holgerbrandl/kscript#declare-dependencies-with-deps">KScript has great support for</a>). On the other hand the second option is probably <strong>easier to implement</strong> because it’s just using the same commands we use everyday on our workflow.</p>

<p>Since I can assume everybody in my team has <code>git</code> and <code>gradle</code> installed and in their path <strong>I went for option 2</strong>.</p>

<h3>Running shell commands from Kotlin</h3>

<p>We can run shell commands on Kotlin using <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/api/java/lang/ProcessBuilder.html"><code>ProcessBuilder</code></a>, just like we’d do from Java.</p>

<p>In this case I’ve created a <code>runCommandWithRedirect</code> extension function that looks like this:</p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code" data-highlight-only>
import java.io.File

//sampleStart
fun String.runCommandWithRedirect(dir: File? = null): ExitStatus {
        return ProcessBuilder("/bin/sh", "-c", this)
            .redirectErrorStream(true)
            .inheritIO()
            .directory(dir)
            .start()
            .waitFor()
}

//sampleEnd
typealias ExitStatus = Int
</xmp>


<p>This function can be called on any String like this:</p>

<p><code>"gradle check".runCommandWithRedirect()</code></p>

<p>This function will:</p>

<ol>
<li>Redirect the standard and error output to the one for the current process, in our case that means <strong>the output of the command will be visible on the terminal when the githook is executed</strong>.</li>
<li>Set the directory to the passed <code>dir</code> parameter, or use the current directory if no parameter is provided.</li>
<li>Execute the command, wait for it to finish and return the <code>ExitStatus</code></li>
</ol>


<p>You can play around with the different <code>ProcessBuilder</code> options. In my script above for example I’ve another version of this function called <code>runCommand</code> that  <strong>executes the command and returns it’s output as a <code>Sequence&lt;String&gt;</code></strong>.</p>

<h2>Automatic installation</h2>

<p>Githooks are great to enforce code quality practices (i.e. <em>”You can’t push if your coverage is less than 80% “</em> 👮). But for the client-side githook to be execute it needs to be in the <code>.git/hooks</code> folder which is not versioned. That means that <strong>each developer on your team has to manually install the hook</strong>, which means that you are again, relying on the good memory of your teammates to enforce code quality.</p>

<p>Instead we could use <a href="https://gist.github.com/KenVanHoeylandt/c7a928426bce83ffab400ab1fd99054a">this trick</a>. We can create a <em>gradle task</em> called <em>“copy”</em> that copies the githook from the <code>src</code> folder to the <code>git/hooks</code> and removes the file extension in the process.</p>

<p>Then we can make the <em>“build”</em> task depend on this new <em>”copy”</em> task. <strong>The next time the developer runs <code>gradle build</code> the githook will be installed</strong>. And as a bonus:  the githook script is now versioned too! <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p>Here’s how this would look like (using <a href="https://github.com/gradle/kotlin-dsl">Kotlin DSL for Gradle</a>)</p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code" data-highlight-only>
tasks {
    "copy"(Copy::class) {
        from("src/main/kotlin/io/jivimberg/githook/pre-push.kts") {
            rename { it.removeSuffix(".kts") }
        }
        into(".git/hooks")
    }

    "build" {
        dependsOn("copy")
    }
}
</xmp>


<p>⚠️ Don’t forget to do <code>chmod u+x Pre-Push.kts</code> to make the script runnable, otherwise it won’t work.</p>

<h2>What about performance?</h2>

<p>Kotlin is a compiled language, so at some point your script will have to be compiled. Fortunately thanks to KScript <strong>this only happens the first time you run the script</strong> and it’s only compiled again if the script changes.</p>

<p>Other than that there’s the JVM startup time which adds <strong>around 200ms of overhead</strong>. Maybe in the future we’ll be able to use <a href="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/reference/native-overview.html">Kotlin Native</a> to compile to native binaries directly and avoid this overhead.</p>

<p>If you want to read more about performance comparison between <em>Python</em> and <em>Kotlin</em> scripts check the <a href="https://github.com/holgerbrandl/kscript#what-are-performance-and-resource-usage-difference-between-scripting-with-kotlin-and-python">KScript documentation</a>.</p>

<h2>Bonus track: testing</h2>

<p>Testing Kotlin scripts turned out <strong>not to be so straight forward.</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://proandroiddev.com/testing-kotlin-scripts-42bbbbe09ae5">This article</a> suggests using a <code>runCommand</code> method similar to the one described above to execute the script and check it’s outputs. Whereas <a href="https://github.com/holgerbrandl/kscript/blob/master/test/TestsReadme.md">KScript own tests</a> are written using <a href="https://github.com/lehmannro/assert.sh">assert.sh</a>.</p>

<p>Neither approach convinced me. I was just looking for a way of <strong>individually test the functions</strong> in my script <strong>using the same tools I use to test the other parts of my code</strong>.</p>

<p>So what I ended up doing was moving all the <em>Pre-Push</em> logic to a regular <code>*.kt</code> file. And then simply creating a <code>*kts</code> Kotlin script that calls my class using the <a href="https://github.com/holgerbrandl/kscript#ease-prototyping-with-include"><code>//INCLUDE</code> KScript directive</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2018-07-04/testing-githook-kotlin.png" title="’Testing githook’" ></p>

<p>The downside is that I know have 2 files for my githook (a <code>*.kt</code> and a <code>*.kts</code>) but that seems <strong>a small price to pay for being able to easily test my code</strong>.</p>

<h1>Conclusion</h1>

<p>Writing githooks in Kotlin is possible and not that hard thanks to <a href="https://github.com/holgerbrandl/kscript">KScript</a>. <strong>You’ll be glad you have tried it out</strong> the next time you have to refactor that <em>pre-push</em> hook.</p>

<p>You can find an <strong>example repository</strong> containing all the code for this blogpost here: <a href="https://github.com/jivimberg/kotlin-githook">https://github.com/jivimberg/kotlin-githook</a></p>

<script src="https://unpkg.com/kotlin-playground@1" data-selector=".kotlin-code"></script>



<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>because you want to verify only on the changes that are going to be pushed<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>And it can even be subject to the same quality standards enforced by the githook itself. INCEPTION!<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oracle, JPA and the Mystery of the String That Was Null]]></title>
    <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2018/06/23/oracle-jpa-and-the-mistery-of-the-string-that-was-null/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-23T10:34:26-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2018/06/23/oracle-jpa-and-the-mistery-of-the-string-that-was-null</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the story of how Oracle DB was messing up Kotlin’s type system, and what I did to fix it.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The setup</h2>

<p>Let’s start by <em>setting the stage</em>, for this particular project I was working with the following stack:</p>

<p><a href="https://developers.redhat.com/promotions/migrating-to-microservice-databases/"><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2018-06-23/Stack.png" width="720" title="’Spring + Data + Kotlin + Oracle’" ></a></p>

<h2>The problem</h2>

<p>So I had modeled the following <strong>Entity</strong> leveraging Kotlin’s <a href="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/reference/data-classes.html">data classes</a><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>:</p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code" data-highlight-only>
import javax.persistence.Entity
import javax.persistence.Id

//sampleStart
@Entity
data class Person(
    val name: String,
    @Id val id: Long? = null
)
//sampleEnd
</xmp>


<p>Tests where passing with flying colors, but for some reason we were noticing that <strong>the <em>name</em> would sometimes come back as <code>null</code></strong> even thought it was typed as <code>String</code> and not <code>String?</code>.</p>

<h2>The analysis</h2>

<p>To make things more difficult there where other failures in the communication layer masking the real issue. But we finally figured out what was happening when we notice <strong>it was only reproducible under the following conditions</strong>:</p>

<ul>
<li>The property <code>name</code> was empty</li>
<li>Not reproducible on tests</li>
<li>Persisting to <em>OracleDB</em> (instead of embedded H2)</li>
</ul>


<p>That’s when I discovered:
<blockquote><p>This is because Oracle internally changes empty string to NULL values. Oracle simply won&rsquo;t let insert an empty string.</p><footer><strong>Some guy on Stack Overflow <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/13278879/1499171">https://stackoverflow.com/a/13278879/1499171</a></strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>So when the data was mapped back to my <code>Person</code> object I ended up with a <code>null</code> value for <em>name</em>. This is probably only possible because <strong>Hibernate is using reflection to set the field value</strong> in runtime, thus breaking Kotlin’s <a href="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/reference/null-safety.html">null safety</a>.</p>

<h2>What I did about it</h2>

<p>The funny thing about this one is that <strong>there is not much you can do about it</strong>. <em>There is no magic configuration to tell Oracle how you want to handle empty strings.</em> Yes there are some hacks like changing <code>""</code> to <code>" "</code> but I’d rather invent a random <em>name</em> for the guy than persisting a whitespace.</p>

<p>The silver lining is that most of the time <strong>if you’re not allowing null values you probably don’t want an empty string either</strong>. Now YMMV but I know this was true for a person’s name.</p>

<p>In fact you might even want to <strong>implement a more strict validation</strong> so people can’t be named: “💩”.</p>

<h3>Testing</h3>

<p>First thing I did was to try to reproduce this using a test. But since I was using <code>@DataJpaTest</code> with H2 embedded DB empty strings where empty strings an nulls where nulls. So the issue was <strong>not reproducible</strong>.</p>

<p>That’s when I learned that you <strong>can tell H2 to behave like an Oracle DB</strong> using <a href="http://www.h2database.com/html/features.html">Oracle Compatibility mode</a>. To achieve this I added the following configuration to my <code>application.yml</code> under <code>test/resources</code>:</p>

<pre><code>spring:
  datasource:
    url: jdbc:h2:mem:testdb;Mode=Oracle
</code></pre>

<p>And annotated my test class with:</p>

<pre><code class="java">@RunWith(SpringRunner::class)
@DataJpaTest
@AutoConfigureTestDatabase(replace = AutoConfigureTestDatabase.Replace.NONE)
class FormRepositoryTest {…}
</code></pre>

<p>And <em>voilà</em>, now you have an <strong>H2 in memory DB dressed up as Oracle</strong>.</p>

<h3>Changing the schema</h3>

<p>The other thing I realized is that <strong>the schema allowed for <code>null</code> values</strong> on the <em>name</em> column. I’d been using <code>javax.persistence.schema-generation</code> as a starting point for my schema and <strong>I wrongly assumed</strong> it would take the hint from the Kotlin type system to prevent null values<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.</p>

<p>Instead I had to explicitly annotate my Entity:</p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code" data-highlight-only>
import javax.persistence.Entity
import javax.persistence.Id

//sampleStart
@Entity
data class Person(
    @Column(nullable = false) val name: String,
    @Id val id: Long? = null
)
//sampleEnd
</xmp>


<p>and manually change my existing schema</p>

<pre><code>CREATE TABLE Person (
  id NUMBER(19, 0) NOT NULL,
  name VARCHAR2(255 CHAR) NOT NULL,
  PRIMARY KEY (id)
);
</code></pre>

<p>The result is that now if somebody tries to persist a Person with an empty name a <strong>big fat Exception is thrown</strong>. Or at least until I implement proper name validation.</p>

<script src="https://unpkg.com/kotlin-playground@1" data-selector=".kotlin-code"></script>



<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>If I had a dollar for every time I modeled a Person…<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>It would be nice right?<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Implementing takeWhileInclusive in Kotlin]]></title>
    <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2018/06/02/implementing-takewhileinclusive-in-kotlin/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-02T13:33:38-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2018/06/02/implementing-takewhileinclusive-in-kotlin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Implementing <code>takeWhileInclusive</code> extension function in Kotlin.</p>

<!--more-->


<blockquote><p>TL,DR (aka <em>“just show me the code”</em> ): <a href="https://gist.github.com/jivimberg/ff5aad3f5c6315deb420fd508a145c61">https://gist.github.com/jivimberg/ff5aad3f5c6315deb420fd508a145c61</a></p></blockquote>

<p>You probably know about <a href="https://kotlinlang.org/api/latest/jvm/stdlib/kotlin.collections/take-while.html"><code>takeWhile</code></a> operation that <strong>returns a List containing the first elements satisfying the given predicate.</strong></p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code">
fun main(args: Array<String>) {
//sampleStart
    val someNumbers = listOf(1, 5, 3, 22, 4, 8, 14, 23, 49, 77, 2, 49)
    println(someNumbers.takeWhile { it % 7 != 0 })
//sampleEnd
}
</xmp>


<p>I was in need of an <strong>inclusive</strong> version of the <code>takeWhile</code>. In other words I needed a function that returned the first elements satisfying the given predicate, <strong>plus the first element that didn’t satisfy it</strong>.</p>

<p>So in the provided example <code>takeWhile</code> returns <code>[1, 5, 3, 22, 4, 8]</code> whereas <code>takeWhileInclusive</code> would return <code>[1, 5, 3, 22, 4, 8, 14] </code> .</p>

<p>A quick search showed me I was not alone. <a href="https://kotlinlang.org/api/latest/jvm/stdlib/kotlin.collections/take-while.html"><em>matklad</em></a> already had a simple implementation working for <code>Sequence</code>:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/54776705250e3b375618f59a8247a237.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>fun &lt;T&gt; Sequence&lt;T&gt;.takeWhileInclusive(pred: (T) -&gt; Boolean): Sequence&lt;T&gt; {
    var shouldContinue = true
    return takeWhile {
        val result = shouldContinue
        shouldContinue = pred(it)
        result
    }
}
</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>Using <strong>extension functions</strong> we are able to add a new function to the standard library type <code>Sequence</code>. If this is your first encounter with an extension function I’d encourage you to read more about them <a href="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/reference/extensions.html#extension-functions">here</a> and then play with them <a href="https://try.kotlinlang.org/#/Kotlin%20Koans/Introduction/Extension%20functions/Task.kt">here</a>.</p>

<p>I found this implementation of <code>takeWhileInclusive</code> quite <strong>elegant</strong>. It uses the original <code>takeWhile</code> with the given predicated, but keeps a <code>shouldContinue</code> variable to delay the predicate evaluation by one step. In other words the evaluation of the predicate passed to <code>takeWhile</code> on element <em>i</em> will actually be the result of applying the predicate function on <em>i - 1</em>. Which if you think about it <em>is exactly what we need</em>. Let’s give it a try:</p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code">
fun <T> Sequence<T>.takeWhileInclusive(
        predicate: (T) -> Boolean
): Sequence<T> {
    var shouldContinue = true
    return takeWhile {
        val result = shouldContinue
        shouldContinue = predicate(it)
        result
    }
}

fun main(args: Array<String>) {
//sampleStart
   val someNumbers = listOf(1, 5, 3, 22, 4, 8, 14, 23, 49, 77, 2, 49).asSequence()
   println(someNumbers.takeWhileInclusive { it % 7 != 0 }.toList())
//sampleEnd
}
</xmp>


<p>This was good! Only <a href="https://gist.github.com/matklad/54776705250e3b375618f59a8247a237#gistcomment-2093675">this comment</a> posted on the original gist made me doubt about the <em>safety</em> of this approach:</p>

<blockquote><p><em>“I love this. If Sequence were parallel, though, wouldn&rsquo;t there be worries about using out-of-closure state?”</em></p></blockquote>

<p>That send me down the rabbit hole and I spent some days reading about <code>parallelStreams</code> and <code>coroutines</code> until I convinced my self the approach was ok.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>With that out of the way I decided to port this solution to be supported in all the places where the <code>takeWhile</code> exists (including <code>String</code> and <code>CharArray</code>). So that <strong>we don’t have to convert to a from a Sequence just to use this function</strong>.</p>

<p>Here’s the end result, ready to be dropped on your project:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/ff5aad3f5c6315deb420fd508a145c61.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>// kotlin.collections

inline fun &lt;T&gt; Array&lt;out T&gt;.takeWhileInclusive(
        predicate: (T) -&gt; Boolean
): List&lt;T&gt; {
    var shouldContinue = true
    return takeWhile {
        val result = shouldContinue
        shouldContinue = predicate(it)
        result
    }
}

inline fun ByteArray.takeWhileInclusive(
        predicate: (Byte) -&gt; Boolean
): List&lt;Byte&gt; {
    var shouldContinue = true
    return takeWhile {
        val result = shouldContinue
        shouldContinue = predicate(it)
        result
    }
}

inline fun ShortArray.takeWhileInclusive(
        predicate: (Short) -&gt; Boolean
): List&lt;Short&gt; {
    var shouldContinue = true
    return takeWhile {
        val result = shouldContinue
        shouldContinue = predicate(it)
        result
    }
}

inline fun IntArray.takeWhileInclusive(
        predicate: (Int) -&gt; Boolean
): List&lt;Int&gt; {
    var shouldContinue = true
    return takeWhile {
        val result = shouldContinue
        shouldContinue = predicate(it)
        result
    }
}

inline fun LongArray.takeWhileInclusive(
        predicate: (Long) -&gt; Boolean
): List&lt;Long&gt; {
    var shouldContinue = true
    return takeWhile {
        val result = shouldContinue
        shouldContinue = predicate(it)
        result
    }
}

inline fun FloatArray.takeWhileInclusive(
        predicate: (Float) -&gt; Boolean
): List&lt;Float&gt; {
    var shouldContinue = true
    return takeWhile {
        val result = shouldContinue
        shouldContinue = predicate(it)
        result
    }
}

inline fun DoubleArray.takeWhileInclusive(
        predicate: (Double) -&gt; Boolean
): List&lt;Double&gt; {
    var shouldContinue = true
    return takeWhile {
        val result = shouldContinue
        shouldContinue = predicate(it)
        result
    }
}

inline fun BooleanArray.takeWhileInclusive(
        predicate: (Boolean) -&gt; Boolean
): List&lt;Boolean&gt; {
    var shouldContinue = true
    return takeWhile {
        val result = shouldContinue
        shouldContinue = predicate(it)
        result
    }
}

inline fun CharArray.takeWhileInclusive(
        predicate: (Char) -&gt; Boolean
): List&lt;Char&gt; {
    var shouldContinue = true
    return takeWhile {
        val result = shouldContinue
        shouldContinue = predicate(it)
        result
    }
}

inline fun &lt;T&gt; Iterable&lt;T&gt;.takeWhileInclusive(
        predicate: (T) -&gt; Boolean
): List&lt;T&gt; {
    var shouldContinue = true
    return takeWhile {
        val result = shouldContinue
        shouldContinue = predicate(it)
        result
    }
}

// kotlin.sequences

fun &lt;T&gt; Sequence&lt;T&gt;.takeWhileInclusive(
        predicate: (T) -&gt; Boolean
): Sequence&lt;T&gt; {
    var shouldContinue = true
    return takeWhile {
        val result = shouldContinue
        shouldContinue = predicate(it)
        result
    }
}

// kotlin.text

inline fun CharSequence.takeWhileInclusive(
        predicate: (Char) -&gt; Boolean
): CharSequence {
    var shouldContinue = true
    return takeWhile {
        val result = shouldContinue
        shouldContinue = predicate(it)
        result
    }
}

inline fun String.takeWhileInclusive(
        predicate: (Char) -&gt; Boolean
): String {
    var shouldContinue = true
    return takeWhile {
        val result = shouldContinue
        shouldContinue = predicate(it)
        result
    }
}</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>Hope you find this useful!</p>

<script src="https://unpkg.com/kotlin-playground@1" data-selector=".kotlin-code"></script>



<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>If you want to read more about my discoveries, check this question at <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/q/50373754/1499171">StackOverflow</a><a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spring Functional Routing]]></title>
    <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2018/05/20/spring-functional-router/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-20T00:16:22-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2018/05/20/spring-functional-router</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is about the clever tricks you can pull with Spring new <strong>functional routing</strong> and it’s Kotlin DSL.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2018-05-19/trainSwitch.jpg" title="’Train switch’" ></p>

<p>Spring 5 introduced the <a href="https://spring.io/blog/2016/09/22/new-in-spring-5-functional-web-framework">Functional Web Framework</a> and with it the ability to do functional routing. Basically instead of annotating your methods with the good old <code>@RequestMapping</code> you can now write functions that go from a <code>Request</code> to a <code>Response&lt;T&gt;</code> (called <code>HandlerFunction&lt;T&gt;</code>). And then use a <code>RouterFunction&lt;T&gt;</code> to map which path will end up in which handler.</p>

<p>Now, for the sake of brevity, I won’t talk about all the benefits of this new functional paradigm. Instead I’d like to focus on <strong>some things that can be done with functional routing that were not possible before</strong>.</p>

<p>I have to admit that <strong>at first</strong> I wasn’t sold on the functional routing thing. Why would I want to replace <code>@RequestMapping</code> with 2 different functions? Isn’t that more code to achieve the same goal? For comparison this is how a <em>simple</em> RoutingFunction could look like<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>:</p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code" data-highlight-only>
    fun router() = router {
        accept(TEXT_HTML).nest {
            GET("/") { permanentRedirect(URI("index.html")).build() }
        }
        "/api".nest {
            accept(APPLICATION_JSON).nest {
                GET("/users", userHandler::findAll)
                POST("/users", userHandler::create)
            }
        }
        resources("/**", ClassPathResource("static/"))
    } 
</xmp>


<p>It’s readable but certainly not as succinct as <code>@GetMapping("/api/users")</code>. But <strong>this terseness comes at the price of expressiveness</strong>. Or as <a href="https://spring.io/blog/2016/09/22/new-in-spring-5-functional-web-framework">this article on Spring.io</a> puts it:</p>

<blockquote><p>The <code>RouterFunction</code> has a similar purpose as a <code>@RequestMapping</code> annotation. However, there is an important distinction: with the annotation <strong>your route is limited to what can be expressed through the annotation values</strong>.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Complex routing</h2>

<p>I’ll use an example to illustrate some of the things that can be achieved with complex routing. Say I have some data modeling a <em>résumé</em> that contains multiple <em>sections</em>. <strong>I want to expose each of this sections as a different REST endpoint</strong>. Underneath we need to handle each call the same way, the only difference is that we’d be processing a different <em>section</em> of data. We could do the routing like this:</p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code" data-highlight-only>
import org.springframework.context.annotation.Bean
import org.springframework.context.annotation.Configuration
import org.springframework.core.io.ClassPathResource
import org.springframework.http.MediaType
import org.springframework.web.reactive.function.server.RouterFunctions.resources
import org.springframework.web.reactive.function.server.router

//sampleStart
    enum class Section(val fieldName: String) {
    PERSONAL_INFO("personalInfo"),
    EXPERIENCE("experience"),
    SIDE_PROJECTS("sideProject"),
    EDUCATION("education"),
}

@Configuration
class Routing {
    @Bean
    fun resumeRouter(handler: ResumeHandler) = router {
        accept(MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON).nest {
            Section.values().forEach {
                GET("/${it.fieldName}", handler.getSectionHandler(it))
            }
        }
    }
}
//sampleEnd

@Component
class ResumeHandler {
fun getSectionHandler(section: Section): (ServerRequest) -\> Mono<ServerResponse> =
            { // get section from data and return response }
}
</xmp>


<p>We can iterate through the enum and create a new mapping for each of the sections with the <code>GET</code> function. Furthermore the function <code>getSectionHandler</code> can receive the enum as parameter and use it for handling the response instead of having to rely only on the <code>ServerRequest</code> context.</p>

<p>Now this is only one of the <em>tricks</em> that can be done with functional routing. Having a <a href="https://spring.io/blog/2017/08/01/spring-framework-5-kotlin-apis-the-functional-way#functional-routing-with-the-kotlin-dsl-for-spring-webflux">Kotlin DSL</a> means we can do <strong>any kind of scripting we can think of</strong> when defining the routes. As always:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2018-05-19/withGreatPower.png" title="’With great power comes great responsibility’" ></p>

<p>Abusing this feature would make your routing logic a <strong>tangled mess</strong>, too hard to understand and maintain. So be smart about it.</p>

<script src="https://unpkg.com/kotlin-playground@1" data-selector=".kotlin-code"></script>



<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Source: [kotlin-swagger-spring-functional-template][2]<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Parallel Map in Java (From Kotlin)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2018/05/07/parallel-map-in-java/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-07T13:19:58-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2018/05/07/parallel-map-in-java</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Following up of my <a href="http://jivimberg.io/blog/2018/05/04/parallel-map-in-kotlin/">previous post</a>, I was curious how a parallel map operation would look like using Java’s <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/Collection.html#parallelStream--"><code>parallelStream</code></a>. Here’s what I find out.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>In Java to use <code>map</code> you do:</p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code">
import java.util.stream.Collectors

//sampleStart
fun main(args: Array<String>) {
    val output = (1..100).toList()
            .stream()
            .map { it * 2 }
            .collect(Collectors.toList())
    println(output)
}
//sampleEnd
</xmp>


<p><em>(In case you’re wondering I’m using Java collections from Kotlin)</em></p>

<p>And to do a <em>parallel</em> <code>map</code> you can simply do:</p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code">
import java.util.stream.Collectors

//sampleStart
fun main(args: Array<String>) {
    val output = (1..100).toList()
            .parallelStream()
            .map { it * 2 }
            .collect(Collectors.toList())
    println(output)
}
//sampleEnd
</xmp>


<p>No need to write a special <code>pmap</code> operation like we did for Kotlin. Just call <code>parallelStream</code> and that’s it. <em>Pretty cool, right?</em></p>

<p>I was curious about how this solution <strong>compared to the one on <a href="http://jivimberg.io/blog/2018/05/04/parallel-map-in-kotlin/">my previous post</a></strong>,  so I decided to time it too.</p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code">
import java.util.stream.Collectors
import kotlin.system.measureTimeMillis

//sampleStart
fun main(args: Array<String>) {
    val time = measureTimeMillis {
        val output = (1..100).toList()
                .parallelStream()
                .map {
                    Thread.sleep(100)
                    it * 2
                }
                .collect(Collectors.toList())

        println(output)
    }

    println("Total time: $time")
}
//sampleEnd
</xmp>


<p>In this case instead I’m actually setting a delay of <strong>100 milliseconds</strong> (instead of <em>1,000</em> like I did on my previous post)<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. I was expecting the total time to be something close to <em>100 milliseconds</em>, just like it was for the Kotlin <code>pmap</code>, <strong>instead I got something close to 5,000</strong>.</p>

<p>Turns out <code>parallelStream</code> uses the default <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/concurrent/ForkJoinPool.html"><em>ForkJoinPool.commonPool</em></a> which by default has a parallelism level <strong>equal to the number of available processors.</strong> In this case 2 processors: <em>100 operations * 100 milliseconds / 2 processors = 5000 milliseconds</em>. You can check the number of available processors simply by adding this line to the script:</p>

<p><code>println(Runtime.getRuntime().availableProcessors())</code></p>

<h2>But, I want more parallelism!</h2>

<p>What if we want to increase the parallelism level? There are <em>2 ways to achieve this.</em></p>

<p><em>The first one</em> is to make our code <strong>run in a custom thread pool</strong> of our choice. Unfortunately Java doesn’t make it easy to provide a custom thread pool, but <a href="http://www.baeldung.com/java-8-parallel-streams-custom-threadpool">the workaround is not so bad either</a>.</p>

<p><em>The other option</em> is to change the <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/concurrent/ForkJoinPool.html"><em>ForkJoinPool.commonPool</em></a> parallelism level by system property like this:</p>

<p><code>System.setProperty("java.util.concurrent.ForkJoinPool.common.parallelism", "10")</code></p>

<p>Unfortunately this doesn’t work on Kotlin Playground so you’ll have to try it on your own machine or take my word that it works.</p>

<p>It’s worth noting that with the second approach you’d still be using the same default thread pool <strong>shared globally across the app</strong>. As you can imagine this can be <strong>EXTREMELY BAD</strong> as you’d be basically depleting resources for the whole application. Some would even argue <a href="https://zeroturnaround.com/rebellabs/java-parallel-streams-are-bad-for-your-health/">this is reason enough not to use <code>parallelStream</code> at all</a>. Although that seems a little extreme if you ask me.</p>

<script src="https://unpkg.com/kotlin-playground@1" data-selector=".kotlin-code"></script>



<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Otherwise the execution takes too long and doesn’t complete. Probably a limitation of Kotlin Playground<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
