<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Data | Coding Forest]]></title>
  <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/categories/data/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2023-06-03T10:56:00-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Juan Ignacio Vimberg]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using UUID on Spring Data JPA Entities]]></title>
    <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2018/11/05/using-uuid-on-spring-data-jpa-entities/"/>
    <updated>2018-11-05T07:25:37-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2018/11/05/using-uuid-on-spring-data-jpa-entities</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this article I’ll explore <strong>how to model a <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/6033905/create-the-perfect-jpa-entity">JPA Entity</a> using an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universally_unique_identifier">UUID</a></strong> as Primary Key working with <a href="https://spring.io/projects/spring-data-jpa">Spring Data JPA.</a></p>

<!--more-->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2018-11-07/uuid.png" title="‘uuid key’" ></p>

<h1>Why UUIDs?</h1>

<p>Usually we use numerical keys on our models and let the DB generate that for us on persistence. But there are <strong>some reasons why you might prefer to use UUIDs</strong> as your Primary Key instead. Namely:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>UUIDs are globally unique.</strong> This means that we don’t need a centralized component to generate unique ids, <strong>we can generate the ids on the application itself</strong> instead of relying on <a href="https://vladmihalcea.com/hibernate-and-uuid-identifiers/">some UUID generator</a> that populates the <code>id</code> field on persist.</li>
<li>Having globally unique ids also means that <strong>your ids are unique across databases.</strong> This allows us to move data across databases without having to check for conflicting ids.</li>
<li>Having application generated ids means the id is known even before the entity is persisted. This lets us <strong>model our entities as <a href="https://proandroiddev.com/kotlin-for-beginners-immutability-and-the-value-of-val-78ab45b60b57">immutable objects</a></strong> and we avoid having to handle null values on the id.</li>
</ul>


<p>But as you probably already know: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/There_ain't_no_such_thing_as_a_free_lunch">🚫🆓🍽</a>. So here are some of the downsides of using UUIDss for you to consider:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Storage space.</strong> As you can imagine storing an UUID takes a lot more space than storying an Int. Specially if you make the mistake of storing it as a <code>String</code>. You might think Id space is not a big deal, but consider that <strong>Primary Keys are often used in indexes and as Foreign Keys on other tables</strong>. So the numbers start to add up.</li>
<li>They are <strong>not human friendly</strong>. What’s easier to remember: <code>223492</code> or <code>453bd9d7-83c0-47fb-b42e-0ab045b29f83 </code>? This is specially true if you happen to be exposing your ids on your public APIs. Think: <code>/albums/2311445/photo/7426321</code> vs <code>/albums/b3480d79-e458-4675-a7ba-61ac5957cb7c/photo/19b24967-1741-4405-a746-d2b081ee45f2 </code>.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>If you’re still on the fence</strong> here’s a great article talking about the pros and cons of using UUIDs as primary keys: <a href="https://tomharrisonjr.com/uuid-or-guid-as-primary-keys-be-careful-7b2aa3dcb439">https://tomharrisonjr.com/uuid-or-guid-as-primary-keys-be-careful-7b2aa3dcb439</a>.</p>

<h1>How to do it</h1>

<p>Now let’s talk about how we can implement this. I’ll go step by step explaining why we add each piece of code.</p>

<p>The first thing we need to do is <strong>generate the UUID</strong>. As mentioned above we’d like to do this on the application code so we can have <em>immutable entities</em>. Generating the UUID is easy, all we need to do is: <code>UUID.randomUUID()</code>. So our entity would look like this:</p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code" theme="darcula" data-highlight-only>
import java.util.\*
import javax.persistence.Id
import javax.persistence.Entity

//sampleStart
@Entity
class Artist(
        @Id val id: UUID = UUID.randomUUID(),
        val name: String
)
//sampleEnd
</xmp>


<p>You’ve probably noticed how we’re making the id an argument of the <a href="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/reference/classes.html#constructors">primary constructor</a>. This is required to <strong>let clients construct entities with known ids to represent persisted objects</strong>. This is useful for example to <strong>model an update operation</strong>: create an enwtity with a known id and updated values, then call <code>save()</code> on such entity.</p>

<h2>isNew?</h2>

<p>As mentioned we’re using <a href="https://spring.io/projects/spring-data-jpa">Spring Data JPA</a> for our Repository layer. Now there’s a small detail we have to take into account when <strong>using application provided ids with Spring Data</strong>. If you do a <code>artistRepository.save(Artist(name = "David Bowie"))</code> you might get an output like this:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2018-11-07/2sql.png" title="‘persist logs’" ></p>

<p>If you pay close attention to the log you’ll notice that <strong>Hibernate is actually executing 2 SQL queries</strong>: one <code>select</code> followed by one <code>insert</code>. Not quite what we were expecting.</p>

<p>The reason for this behavior is the implementation of Spring Data’s <a href="https://github.com/spring-projects/spring-data-jpa/blob/master/src/main/java/org/springframework/data/jpa/repository/support/SimpleJpaRepository.java"><code>SimpleJpaRepository.java</code></a>. In particular the <a href="https://github.com/spring-projects/spring-data-jpa/blob/01e36dbb44d6bc87f7deb3b6d6dacc955ea6c8bd/src/main/java/org/springframework/data/jpa/repository/support/SimpleJpaRepository.java#L506"><code>save()</code></a> method:</p>

<pre><code class="java">@Transactional
public &lt;S extends T&gt; S save(S entity) {
    if (entityInformation.isNew(entity)) {
        em.persist(entity);
        return entity;
    } else {
        return em.merge(entity);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p><strong>The double SQL statement is caused by the call to <code>merge()</code></strong>. By default the way this class decides whether to do a <code>persist()</code> or a <code>merge()</code> <strong>is simply by checking if the id is null</strong>. Which works fine for DB assigned ids, but <em>not</em> for application assigned ones. 😕</p>

<p><strong>The best way to control this is by implementing the <a href="https://github.com/spring-projects/spring-data-commons/blob/master/src/main/java/org/springframework/data/domain/Persistable.java"><code>Persistable&lt;ID&gt;</code></a> interface</strong> providing a <code>isNew()</code> method. Since this is something we’ll want to do every time we use application generated UUIDs <strong>I’ll extract this into an abstract class</strong> and making use of the <code>@MappedSuperClass</code> annotation.</p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code" theme="darcula" data-highlight-only>
import org.springframework.data.domain.Persistable
import java.util.\*
import javax.persistence.\*

//sampleStart
@MappedSuperclass
abstract class AbstractBaseEntity(givenId: UUID? = null) : Persistable<UUID> {

    @Id
    @Column(name = "id", length = 16, unique = true, nullable = false)
    private val id: UUID = givenId ?: UUID.randomUUID()
    
    @Transient
    private var persisted: Boolean = givenId != null
    
    override fun getId(): UUID = id
    
    override fun isNew(): Boolean = !persisted
    
    override fun hashCode(): Int = id.hashCode()
    
    override fun equals(other: Any?): Boolean {
        return when {
            this === other -> true
            other == null -> false
            other !is AbstractBaseEntity -> false
            else -> getId() == other.getId()
        }
    }
    
    @PostPersist
    @PostLoad
    private fun setPersisted() {
        persisted = true
    }
}
//sampleEnd

</xmp>


<blockquote><p>This design was <strong>suggested to me by <a href="https://twitter.com/PabloHernanS">@paschmid</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/rcruzjo">@rcruzjo</a></strong>, this code would be quite ugly if it weren’t for them!</p></blockquote>

<p>You can see how the <code>persisted</code> state is decided based on whether an id is provided on creation or not, to account for updates. Also notice how <strong>its value gets automatically updated upon <em>persist</em> and <em>load</em></strong> thanks to <code>@PostPersist</code> and <code>@PostLoad</code> annotations.</p>

<p>Also since <code>id</code> is now <em>unique</em> and <em>non-nullable</em> <strong>we can use it to implement <code>equals()</code> and <code>hashcode()</code></strong> and avoid falling in some of the common pitfalls of implementing this methods (to learn more about this check <a href="https://vladmihalcea.com/how-to-implement-equals-and-hashcode-using-the-jpa-entity-identifier/">this article</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/vlad_mihalcea">@vlad_mihalcea</a> and <a href="https://kotlinexpertise.com/hibernate-with-kotlin-spring-boot/">this one</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/s1m0nw1">@s1m0nw1</a>).</p>

<p>And in case you’re wondering <strong>why we need an explicit <code>getId()</code> function</strong>, it is because of this issue: <a href="https://youtrack.jetbrains.com/issue/KT-6653">Kotlin properties do not override Java-style getters and setters</a>.</p>

<h1>Putting it all together</h1>

<p>Finally let’s see how a concrete entity would use this.</p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code" theme="darcula" data-highlight-only>
import org.springframework.data.repository.CrudRepository
import java.util.\*
import javax.persistence.Entity

//sampleStart
@Entity
class Artist(
        id: UUID? = null,
        val name: String
) : AssignedIdBaseEntity(id)
//sampleEnd
</xmp>


<p>Pretty similar to our original approach right? Thanks to the abstract class all the <code>isNew()</code> <strong>implementation details are hidden</strong> from concrete entities.</p>

<p>And now if we do a <code>save()</code> on a new entity <strong>we get one single SQL statement</strong> as we were expecting.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2018-11-07/1sql.png" width="600" title="‘persist logs with abstractEntity’" ></p>

<hr />

<h1>Approach 2: Making it simpler with @Version</h1>

<p>This approach was suggested by <a href="https://disqus.com/by/disqus_UhNaTY8OWI/">Diego Marin</a> in the comments.</p>

<p>Spring Data can leverage the existence of a <code>@Version</code> field to tell if the Entity is present or not. By having <code>@Version</code>, we also get <a href="https://www.baeldung.com/jpa-optimistic-locking">Optimistic Locking</a> for free.</p>

<xmp class="kotlin-code" theme="darcula" data-highlight-only>
import java.util.*
import javax.persistence.Column
import javax.persistence.Entity
import javax.persistence.Id
import javax.persistence.Version

//sampleStart
@Entity
class Celeb(
        @Id @Column(name = "id", length = 16, unique = true, nullable = false)
        val id: UUID = UUID.randomUUID(),
        @Version
        val version: Long? = null,
        val name: String
) {
    override fun equals(other: Any?) = when {
        this === other -> true
        javaClass != other?.javaClass -> false
        id != (other as Celeb).id -> false
        else -> true
    }

    override fun hashCode(): Int = id.hashCode()
}
//sampleEnd
</xmp>


<blockquote><p>⚠️ Make sure you’re importing <code>javax.persistence.Version</code> and NOT <code>org.springframework.data.annotation.Version</code>!</p></blockquote>

<p>We still need to write the <code>id</code> column definition and <code>equal</code> and <code>hashCode</code> methods, so if this is something you’ll be applying in most of your entities you might want to consider extracting it to a superclass. Similar to what we did with <code>AssignedIdBaseEntity</code>, but using <code>@Version</code></p>

<hr />

<p>You can find all the <strong>code samples</strong> for this post on <strong><a href="https://github.com/jivimberg/spring-data-uuid-example">this GitHub repo</a></strong>.</p>

<p><img class="right-fill" src="/images/signatures/signature1.png" width="200" title="‘My signature’" ></p>

<script src="https://unpkg.com/kotlin-playground@1" data-selector=".kotlin-code"></script>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Recomendations: Migrating to Microservices Databases]]></title>
    <link href="http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2018/05/25/book-recomendations-migrating-to-microservices-databases/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-25T07:32:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jivimberg.github.io/blog/2018/05/25/book-recomendations-migrating-to-microservices-databases</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just finished reading <em> Migrating to microservices databases</em> by <a href="https://twitter.com/yanaga">Edson Yanaga</a>. If you can relate to the 3 nouns in the title then you’ll want to check it out.</p>

<!--more-->


<blockquote><p>Code is easy; state is hard.</p>

<p>— <em>Edson Yanaga</em></p></blockquote>

<p>If you are on the journey of <strong>migrating your monolith to a micro-service architecture</strong> (like every other developer this days) then, at some point, you probably found yourself staring at a whiteboard full of rectangles and hexagons thinking: <em>where does the data fit in this mess?</em></p>

<p>Maybe you’ve read about the <a href="http://microservices.io/patterns/data/database-per-service.html">“Database per service”</a> pattern and now you’re wondering what your requirements are on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consistency_(database_systems)">data consistency</a>. Or somebody told you about <a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/CQRS.html">CQRS</a> but you don’t know it’s advantages and disadvantages.</p>

<p><a href="https://developers.redhat.com/promotions/migrating-to-microservice-databases/"><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2018-05-26/MigratingToMicroservicesDatabases.png" title="’Migrating to Micro-services databases book cover’" ></a></p>

<p>Edson’s book opens with a brief recap of the micro-service world. Going from <em>“Why microservices”</em> to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A/B_testing">A/B testing</a> and <a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/CanaryRelease.html">Canary deployment</a>, the book provides a <strong>super-quick explanation of each concept without going into many details.</strong></p>

<p>By contrast the second part of the book deeps dive into <strong>how to handle the data</strong> of your micro-services. <em>Chapter 3</em> explains how to do <strong>Zero downtime migration</strong> of your relational DB and which tools to use.</p>

<p>On <em>Chapter 4</em> Edson introduces the different <strong>consistency models</strong> and compares <strong>CRUD Vs. CQRS</strong> (explaining also <em>Event sourcing</em>)</p>

<p><strong>The last chapter is, to me, the best.</strong> <em>Chapter 5</em>  contains a recount and description of some of the different <strong>Integration Strategies</strong> we might want to consider when <em>migrating the monolith</em>. Each strategy is briefly described, and we are also provided with an assessment of <strong>applicability</strong> and section of <strong>considerations</strong> to keep in mind if using this strategy.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>The hardest part of design is not knowing the architectural patterns or the different techniques to solve a problem, but <strong>knowing which solution is a good fit to which problem.</strong> Yanaga’s book serves as a good <strong>catalog of possible solutions</strong> to consider, when working with data on micro-services. It provides a concise analysis of each <strong>strategy</strong> and helps us avoid those  <em>”I wish I’ve thought this better before writing the code”</em> moments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
